Padraic Colum Papers
Padraic Colum Papers
- Writings
  - Travel
    - From coast to coast: An Irish lecturer's tour, typescript; covers several U.S. cities (Box 6)
    - Nassau, 1962; clipping from Vogue magazine (Box 6)
    - Tour in Australia, 1967; mix of typescript and typescript carbons; includes two sheets of expenses (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - By an Irish fireside, 1935; script for episode of radio show; story is "The Hen Wife's Son and Princess Bright Brow" (Box 6)
    - Cabell letters, photocopies of letters to and from James Branch Cabell, noted as "kept to refer back to in case of questions" (Box 6)
    - Gulliver's Travels: Introduction, galleys with corrections (Box 6)
    - Irish Arts and Literary Society bulletin article, 1950; summary of year's activity (Box 6)
    - Lynch law notes, photocopies of typed notes (Box 6)
    - Lysippus, single typed sheet with lengthy quote from E. A. Gardner (Box 6)
    - Preface to Stephen McKenna by E. R. Dodds, galleys (Box 6)
    - Speech to Academy of Irish Letters, 1954; acceptance speech upon bestowing of Society's medal; photocopy of typescript (Box 6)
    - Tales of Thimble Castle, Episode 2, "The King of the Cats"; script, probably for radio show (Box 6)
    - Unidentified autobiographical, fragments; mix of typescript and typescript carbon (Box 6)
    - Unidentified introduction (Box 6)
    - Unidentified, begins "Les romanciers...", small sheets, handwritten in pencil; in French (Box 6)
    - Photocopies of published work, pages from The Vegetable Kingdom, A Poet's Circuits, etc. (Box 6)
  - By others
    - Casto, Robert Clayton / Attis, typescript of poem (Box 6)
    - Gordan, John D. / A legend revisited: Elinor Wylie, reprint (Box 6)
    - Jordan, Philip / A tale to make your hair stand on end, 1963; small chapbook printed by Overbrook Press (Box 6)
    - Kennelly, Brendan / A drinking cup: Poems from the Irish, 1970; printed by Allen Figgis, Dublin; signed and inscribed by the author to Padraic (Box 6)
    - MacEntee, Marie / A heart full of thoughts: Translations from the Irish, 1959; printed by Dolmen Press (Box 6)
    - McAleer, Edward C. / The ignorance of Bloom, 1961; reprint; signed and inscribed by the author (Box 6)
    - O'Kelly, M. / The Parnellites, typescript crabon of preface (Box 6)
    - Postgate, H. W. / The Reverend Nicholas Sheehy, 1931; typescript, dated at the end (Box 6)
    - Raine, Kathleen / The responsibility of the poet, 1961; typescript (Box 6)
  - Unidentified
    - Miscellaneous, prose, poetry and music fragments, author undetermined; mix of typescript, typescript carbons, a few handwritten items (Box 6)
- Padraic Colum Estate
  - Correspondence
    - Allen Figgis & Co., 1972; 1975-1976; correspondence (Box 7)
    - ASCAP (American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers), 1970-1978; 1982-1983; correspondence, royalty statement, copies of checks, etc. (Box 7)
    - Australian Broadcasting Commission, 1971; 1979,; 1982; permissions (Box 7)
    - Boosey & Hawkes, 1909; 1913,; 1969-1976,; 1981-1982; two earliest items are photocopies, not originals (Box 7)
    - British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC), 1978; 1980,; 1983; permissions (Box 7)
    - Browne & Nolan, 1958; photocopy of contract for Life of Arthur Griffith (Box 7)
    - Caedmon, 1970; 1977-1978; royalty statements (Box 7)
    - Cahill, Gerald, See Legal: Cahill, Stone and Driscoll.
    - Campbell, Joseph, undated; photocopy of letter from Emmet to Campbell (Box 7)
    - Charles E. Merrill, 1971; permissions (Box 7)
    - Claddagh Records Ltd., 1970; includes photocopies of unsigned recording contracts (Box 7)
    - Clarendon Press, 1972-1974; permissions (Box 7)
    - Colin Smythe Ltd., 1977-1978; 1981; includes unsigned draft of contract (Box 7)
    - Collier Books, 1968-1970; royalty statements (Box 7)
    - Colum Foundation, 1973; undated; includes photocopy of letter from Gerald Cahill to Frances Steloff of Gotham Book Mart (Box 7)
    - Crowell-Collier, 1961; photocopy of contract for Poetry of Jonathan Swift (Box 7)
    - Crown Publishers, 1949; 1969-1977; correspondence, contracts, royalty statements (Box 7)
    - Devin Adair, 1953; 1959-1977; contract for Collected Poems, royalty statements (Box 7)
    - Evans Brothers Ltd., 1973-1974; permissions (Box 7)
    - Faber & Faber, 1976; permissions (Box 7)
    - Folkways, 1967-1970; correspondence, royalty statements (Box 7)
    - Funeral arrangements, 1972 (Box 7)
    - Grosset & Dunlap, 1958; 1969-1982; photocopies of contract for Myths of the World, correspondence, royalty statements (Box 7)
    - Harcourt Brace Jovanovich (also includes earlier firm names), 1969-1972; 1983; permissions (Box 7)
    - Holt, Rinehart & Winston, 1971; permissions (Box 7)
    - Houghton Mifflin, 1971; 1976-1977; permissions (Box 7)
    - Indiana University Press, 1953; memorandum of agreement for The Vegetable Kingdom (Box 7)
    - Irish Arts Council, 1976; correspondence with Mary Lavin, Colm O'Briain (Box 7)
    - Irish Tourist Board (Bord Fáilte Eireann), 1972; correspondence with Elizabeth Healy, permissions, photocopy of material relating to exhibit "Padraic Colum at 87" (Box 7)
    - Krochalis, Edmund, 1972; letter detailing the Krochalis' assistance to Padraic in his later years (Box 7)
    - Macmillan
      See also Padraic and Mary Colum: Correspondence: Macmillan
      - Contracts, 1931; 1961,; 1964-1965,; 1967; contracts for Poems, The King of Ireland's Son, Roofs of Gold, The Boy Apprenticed to the Enchanter, The Girl Who Sat by the Ashes, Storytelling Old and New (Box 7)
      - Correspondence, 1967; 1970-1983 (Box 7)
      - Royalties, 1967-1982; statements, copies of checks, etc. (Box 7)
    - Magnus, Freda, 1955; 1963-1965,; 1970,; 1972-1975; Ms. Magnus was Emmet's assistant for a period of time and Emmet was apparently later her executor as well; unclear whether the financial material in this folder relates to her or to Padraic (Box 7)
    - McGraw-Hill
      See also Padraic Colum: Correspondence: McGraw-Hill.
      - Contracts, 1965; 1969; photocopies of contract for Stone of Victory, The White Sparrow, Anthology of Folk Tales (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1977 (Box 8)
      - Royalties, 1969-1971; 1976 (Box 8)
    - New York Times, 1972 (Box 8)
    - O'Sullivan, Maisie (Maire), 1971-1981 (Box 8)
      See also Padraic Colum: Correspondence: O'Sullivan, Maisie
    - Oxford University Press, 1970; 1983; contract for The Poet's Circuit, correspondence, permissions, royalties (Box 8)
    - Publishers, miscellaneous, 1970-1982; correspondence, permissions (Box 8)
    - Radio Telefís Éireann, 1971-1972; 1975; correspondence, permissions (Box 8)
    - Rights and permissions, miscellaneous, 1968-1982 (Box 8)
    - St. Fintan's Graveyard, 1972-1974; correspondence with Niall Montgomery, attorneys about Padraic's gravestone, maintenance of grave, etc. (Box 8)
    - Samuel French, 1970; royalty statements (Box 8)
    - Sound Seminars, 1970; memorandum of agreement for tape recordings (Box 8)
    - South African Broadcasting Corporation, 1971-1976; permissions (Box 8)
    - Spoken Arts, 1956; 1969-1970; photocopy of contract for Irish verse recordings, royalty statements (Box 8)
    - University College, Dublin, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Vaugh, Helen, 1976-1983 (Box 8)
    - Yale University Press, 1969-1977; correspondence, royalty statements (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous A-Z and unidentified, 1967-1977 (Box 8)
  - Financial
    - Bank accounts, 1969-1983; lists, statements, etc. (Box 8)
    - Royalty lists, undated; handwritten and typed lists of publishers and amounts (Box 8)
    - Taxes, 1962-1983 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, assorted bills and finance-related correspondence (Box 8)
  - Legal
    - Cahill, Stone and Driscoll, 1972-1976; includes personal letter from Gerald Cahill, clippings about his conviction for embezzlement (Box 8)
    - Charles T. Rice, 1969-1971; includes list of next-of-kin (Box 8)
    - Inventory of books (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969-1982; attorneys and law firms, including Bolton-Jones & Co. and Vittoria, King and Parker (Box 8)